1909 Hudson-Fulton Celebration Collection
Marist College Archives and Special Collections
1909 Hudson-Fulton Celebration Collection
1901-2009
1908-1910
NPKMC-224-111
Allen and Susan Fink
22.97 Linear Feet
The 1909 Hudson-Fulton Celebration Collection, c. 1901-2009, contains materials and souvenirs associated with the commemorative celebration. The Hudson-Fulton Celebration commemorated the 300th anniversary of Henry Hudson’s discovery of the Hudson River and the 100th anniversary of Robert Fulton’s first successful commercial application of the paddle steamboat. The collection was created by Allen Fink and Susan Bette Fink (nee Budson). They devoted years to researching and collecting Hudson-Fulton Celebration items to create a comprehensive collection of materials telling the event's story.
Marist College Archives and Special Collections 3399 North Rd Poughkeepsie New York 12601 United States
There are no restrictions on this collection
The Hudson-Fulton Celebration commemorated the 300th anniversary of Henry Hudson's discovery of the Hudson River and the 100th anniversary of Robert Fulton's first successful commercial application of the paddle steamboat. The collection was created by Allen Fink and Susan Bette Fink (nee Budson). They devoted years to researching and collecting Hudson-Fulton Celebration items to create a comprehensive collection of materials telling the event's story. The Fink's collection was recognized for its excellence while featured in a 2009 exhibition celebrating the 100th anniversary of the 1909 Hudson-Fulton Celebration at the New York State Museum in Albany. Allen Fink (1934-2020), a native of Brooklyn, NY, and Passaic, NJ, was born in 1934. Allen attended public school until he left school and home at 16. He worked various odd jobs - laborer, butcher's apprentice, tool, and dye-maker until he joined the United States Air Force at 19. While in the USAF, Allen went to school to become a radar technician. Later, he served 18 months in Morocco, working for Strategic Air Command. He explored the various cities nearby and learned about the history and local customs. Although Allen had not finished high school, he continued his education through reading, always going to the local library in his community or near his military base, reading anything and everything. Upon returning to New Jersey in 1959, he attended classes to complete his GED. Under the Veteran's GI Bill, Allen entered the Newark Institute of Technology, now the New Jersey Institute of Technology. During his college years, he worked one summer in Israel, affiliated with Technion, the Israel Institute of Technology, on telephone communications systems. During this time of national insecurity, he was required to become a temporary resident to do work in Israel. Allen's travels sparked an interest in history, and he began collecting stamps during travel from various locations. This led to his lifelong passion for collecting other materials, including postcards, coins, maps, prints, toys, comic books, and other types of ephemera. His specialties included the United States, France, the Hudson-Fulton Celebration, Early Flight, Zeppelins, the Civil War, and Judaica. Allen married Enid Reisberg of Newburgh, NY, and they had two children, Steven and Joli Anna. He then continued his education and earned a Master's degree in Industrial Management from Union College. After college, he began working in the Eclipse Pioneer Division of Bendix Aviation Corporation. In 1964, after several years in Advanced Research and Development, Allen left Bendix and joined International Business Machines (IBM) in Poughkeepsie, NY. At IBM, he worked in the research and development of mainframes until his retirement in 1993. After Allen retired from IBM, he continued to pursue his passion for collecting. In 1997, he married Susan Budson, who joined him in his varied endeavors, including table tennis and competition, and shared his passion for collecting. Post-retirement, Allen joined Vassar College as their Table Tennis Coach, was an active member of Vassar Temple, and taught classes at IBM and Marist College Center for Lifetime Studies. In his life, Allen encouraged people to pursue their interests and passions, learn, and be the best they could be.
The 1909 Hudson-Fulton Celebration Collection, c. 1901-2009, features materials associated with the commemorative celebration. The Hudson-Fulton Celebration commemorated the 300th anniversary of Henry Hudson’s discovery of the Hudson River and the 100th anniversary of Robert Fulton’s first successful commercial application of the paddle steamboat. The celebration occurred between September 25th and October 9th, 1909. The jubilant celebration surrounded the achievements of both Hudson and Fulton and the importance of the Hudson River to New York City and New York State. Events took place at various locations along the Hudson River from North New Jersey to Upstate New York over the course of two weeks. The various items in the collection showcase how Americans celebrated and revered the event. The collection contains postcards, photographs, advertising, medallions, plaques, pennants, medals, pins, badges, books, and many other items commemorating the 1909 Hudson-Fulton Celebration.
Hudson, Henry, -1611; Hudson-Fulton Celebration, 1909; Hudson River Valley (N.Y. and N.J.)
Collection is arranged into 11 series: 1) Postcards, 2) Photographs, 3) Souvenirs and Plates, 4) Spoons, 5) Textiles, 6) Publications, containing two subseries, 7) Coins, 8) Badges, Medals, and Pins, containing two subseries, 9) Fobs, 10) Musical Instrument- Zither, 11) Miscellany
- 1. Postcards, 1901-1909; 1.0 linear feet 1 Box (Box 1)
  Postcards and commemorative USPS materials associated with and created for The 1909 Hudson-Fulton Celebration.
  - Fidelity Trust Co. Bank of Livonia Postcard (Box 1)
    Postcard contain Hudson Fulton Celebration Program historical fact on “Public Burning of the Newspapers 1733.” Front depicts colonial scene of Hudson River Valley’s Bank of Livonia in Livonia, NY
  - Greene County Day Postcard (Box 1)
    Depicts black and white image of celebration on the Hudson in Catskill, NY on October 6, 1909. Card contains advertisement for Catskill tourism.
  - Fishkill-on-Hudson Postcard (Box 1)
    Depicts black and white image of Mount Beacon and Incline Railroad. Advertisement for Fishkill tourism and Hammond’s “Cattle Comfort” Product.
  - Alfred Benjamin & Co. Troop A Postcard (Box 1)
    Depicts color image of Troop A as they move up 5th Avenue in New York City. Postcard courtesy of Alfred Benjamin and Co.
  - Fulton Trust Co. Tuck’s Postcard (Box 1)
    Postcard contains a short bio for Robert Fulton and the proposed program for the Hudson Fulton Celebration. Front color image is a textured depiction of Robert Fulton with a model of his "Clermont."
  - Hudson-Fulton Flag Postcard (Box 1)
    Front color image depicts the Dutch East India Company flag used by Henry Hudson on his voyage up the Hudson. Card is an advertisement for the sale of the reproduction flag by William G. White.
  - B.B. Williamson, D.D.S. Hudson-Fulton Postcard (Box 1)
    Depicts black and white photo of “The Court of Honor” in Poughkeepsie, NY. Photograph is by F.B. Howard. Postcard compliments of Williamson D.D.S.
  - Monument at Fishkill Postcard (Box 1)
    Depicts black and white image of a Revolutionary Monument erected by the Melzingah Chapter of the Daughters of the American Revolution on October 14, 1897. Card features advertisement for Hammond's brand paint.
  - Hudson HF Celebration Postcard (Box 1)
    Image depicts Hudson Boat Club in Hudson, NY illuminated for “Hudson-Fulton” Celebration.
  - Morris, NY Hudson-Fulton Celebration Postcard (Box 1)
    Depicts black and white photo from the Hudson-Fulton parade in Morris, NY.
  - Brooklyn Memorial Arch Postcard (Box 1)
    Depicts a texturized sketch of the Memorial Arch in Brooklyn, NY. “Hudson-Fulton Celebration” printed in purple along top left.
  - Broadway in Newburgh Postcard, Some damage to front image where scratching is along the top center to right. (Box 1)
    Depicts black and white photo of Broadway in Newburgh, NY illuminated for the Hudson-Fulton Celebration.
  - Grand Street Newburgh Postcard, Some light scratches and fingerprints on image. Small stain on the front bottom right. (Box 1)
    Depicts black and white photo of the Court House and Grand Street in Newburgh,NY illuminated for the Hudson Fulton Celebration.
  - Broadway from City Hall Newburgh Postcard, Small fold in the upper left corner. Each corner also features slight discoloration and indentation from previous storage. (Box 1)
    Depicts black and white photo of Broadway from City Hall in Newburgh, NY illuminated for Hudson-Fulton Celebration.
  - Newburgh Waterfront Hudson-Fulton Celebration Postcard (Box 1)
    Features a color image depicting the Hudson-Fulton Celebration along the riverfront in Newburgh,NY. Copyright of The News Company Newburgh.
  - Poughkeepsie Court Honor Postcard (Box 1)
    Depicts black and white photo of the Court Honor in Poughkeepsie, NY illuminated for Hudson-Fulton Celebration.
  - Ilium Building Troy Postcard, Light staining on front, upper left corner and along top. USPS ink stamped across front of image, along top left to middle. (Box 1)
    Depicts photo of the Ilium Building, Fourth and Fulton Streets in Troy, NY decorated for the Hudson-Fulton Celebration.
  - Troy Grand Court of Honor East Postcard (2 copies) (Box 1)
    Depicts black and white photo of the Grand Court of Honor, Broadway, and 3rd Street in Troy, NY looking East. The banner displayed for the Hudson-Fulton Celebration reads “Hudson-Fulton Troy, NY”.
  - Troy Old Dutch Windmill Postcard (Box 1)
    Depicts black and white photo of the Old Dutch Windmill in Franklin Square in Troy, NY. Square and windmill are decorated/illuminated for Hudson-Fulton Celebration.
  - Troy River Street Postcard, Small creases in front, upper right corner. Light staining in front, upper right down to center right. USPS ink across top, center of image. (Box 1)
    Depicts black and white photo of River Street in Troy, NY looking North. Showcases the street’s decorations for the Hudson-Fulton Celebration.
  - Troy Court of Honor West Postcard (Box 1)
    Depicts black and white/sepia image of the Court of Honor in Troy, NY looking West. Hudson-Fulton Celebration banner reads “Clermont Troy, NY”.
  - Hudson-Fulton Celebration Parade Troy Postcard (Box 1)
    Depicts black and white photo of Hudson-Fulton Celebration parade in Troy, NY.
  - Illuminated Old Dutch Windmill Troy Postcard, Faint USPS ink along front of image top to middle. (Box 1)
    Depicts black and white image of the Old Dutch Mill in Troy, NY illuminated and decorated for the Hudson-Fulton Celebration.
  - Embossed Banner S.S. Clermont Postcard, Image is discolored/faded. Envelope is very brittle and contains small creases throughout and tears along the edges. (Box 1)
    Gold embossed postcard depicting image of Fulton’s “S.S. Clermont” along with golden banner, golden eagle, and the American flag. Envelope for card included.
  - Embossed S.S. Clermont Postcard (Box 1)
    Gold embossed postcard depicting image of Fulton’s “S.S. Clermont” along with a golden eagle and the American flag.
  - Embossed Cartoon Hudson-Fulton Postcard, Faint USPS ink across left center of image. Large scratch from center to left center of image. (Box 1)
    Embossed postcard with embossed lettering and image depicting a cartoon of a colonial man smoking a pipe while overlooking the Hudson River Valley and ship on the river.
  - Universal Bus. Inst. Trifold Hudson-Fulton Postcard, Paper is very delicate. Small stain on front upper left corner and middle bottom along edge. (Box 1)
    Trifold postcard courtesy of the Universal Business Institute of NYC featuring images of Hudson, Fulton, “Clermont,” and “Half-Moon”. Card opens to an advertisement for the institute.
  - Hudson-Fulton Ships Foldout Postcard, Paper is very fragile along folds. Some staining and damage to image of “Half-Moon” and to the right of image of “Clermont” (potentially water damage). (Box 1)
    Postcard features drawn depictions of “Clermont,” “Half-Moon,” and the new steamship used for the Hudson-Fulton Celebration. The card also opens to short bios for both Fulton and Hudson.
  - Hudson-Fulton Men of War Postcard, Slight creasing and very faint staining along back of postcard. (Box 1)
    Foldout postcard depicting color image of steamships, “Clermont,” and “Half-Moon” escorted up the Hudson River by the United States Men of War and balloons.
  - Hudson-Fulton Men of War Postcard #2 (Box 1)
  - Hudson-Fulton Men of War Postcard #3, Pieces are separated from one another and are missing the third piece of foldout. Fraying along edges where they were once connected together. Faint staining across top front of first portion. (Box 1)
  - P. Sanders S.S. Clermont Postcard (Box 1)
    Depicts color image of Fulton’s “S.S. Clermont” on the Hudson River. Copyright P. Sanders. Labelled 405/10.
  - P. Sanders Half-Moon Postcard (Box 1)
    Depicts color image of Hudson’s “Half-Moon” on the Hudson River. Copyright P. Sanders. Labelled 405/3.
  - Gilded U.S.S. Lusitania Postcard, Gilded ship has the potential to push through back of card. Discoloration around edges of back of card. (Box 1)
    Postcard featuring gilded image of Lusitania along with gilded lettering reading “Souvenir of Hudson-Fulton Celebration”. Background depicts color image of a river bank. Labelled 5981.
  - Gilded Steamship Postcard, Gilded steamship has begun to puncture through back of card. (Box 1)
    ostcard features gilded image of steamship amongst onlookers on the Hudson River. Gilded lettering reads “Souvenir of Hudson-Fulton Celebration”. Labelled 9581.
  - Gilded Lifeboat in Breakers Postcard, Rust on bottom left of gilded ship. Rips on back where gilded ship has punctured through the paper. (Box 1)
    Postcard features gilded image of steamship and lettering reading “Souvenir of Hudson-Fulton Celebration”. Background features color image of lighthouse and other nautical images.
  - Gilded/Bejeweled Hudson-Fulton Postcard, Some glitter and jewels are missing from lettering, revealing the glue beneath. There is staining where missing jewels were. (Box 1)
    Depicts image of Hudson, Fulton, and “Clermont” on orange, white, and blue card. Large, gilded/bejeweled lettering across card reads “Hudson-Fulton Celebration Greetings”.
  - Reproduction Wood-Block Clermont Postcard (Box 1)
    Features reproduction image from a wood block engraving of the “Clermont” on its voyage up the Hudson River. Reproduction done by “Things Remembered” in Oradell, NJ.
  - Silk Hudson Portrait Postcard, Discoloration on back corners from previous storage. (Box 1)
    Embossed postcard with silk black and white image depicting Hudson and “Half-Moon”.
  - Silk Fulton Portrait Postcard (Box 1)
    Embossed postcard with silk black and white image depicting Fulton and “Clermont”.
  - Silk American Flag Hudson-Fulton Celebration Postcard, Flag is very fragile and cracked in several places. (Box 1)
    Embossed postcard featuring a silk
  - Verplanck’s Point Postcard, Creases visible in top right corner. (Box 1)
    Depicts black and white photo of Verplanck’s Point on the Hudson River—the original intended site for the permanent international exposition. Comes with document explaining why site was not turned into permanent exposition.
  - Verplanck’s Point Postcard #2 (Box 1)
  - B&W Koehler Half-Moon Discovery Postcard (Box 1)
    Depicts black and white portrait of Hudson with background image of Native Americans observing “Half-Moon” on the banks of Hudson River.
  - Color Koehler Half-Moon Discovery Postcard (Box 1)
    Depicts color portrait of Hudson with background image of Native Americans observing “Half-Moon” on the banks of the Hudson River. Par Excellence Series Hudson River No. 2.
  - B&W Koehler Half-Moon Postcard (Box 1)
    Depicts black and white portrait of Hudson with background image of Native Americans observing “Half-Moon” on one bank of Hudson River.
  - Color Koehler Half-Moon Postcard, Crease across Hudson portrait in upper left corner. Faint discoloration of corners from past storage. (Box 1)
    Depicts color portrait of Hudson with background image of Native Americans observing “Half-Moon” on one bank of Hudson River.
  - Texturized Color Koehler Half-Moon Postcard (Box 1)
    Depicts texturized, color portrait of Hudson with background image of Native Americans observing “Half-Moon” on one bank of Hudson River. Par Excellence Series Hudson River No. 3.
  - B&W Koehler Clermont Journey Postcard, Faint staining on front upper left corner. (Box 1)
    Depicts black and white portrait of Fulton and background image of “Clermont” on Hudson with onlooking colonists.
  - Color Koehler Clermont Journey Postcard, Slight discoloration of corners from past storage. (Box 1)
    Depicts color portrait of Fulton and background image of “Clermont” on Hudson with onlooking colonists.
  - Texturized Color Koehler Clermont Journey Postcard (Box 1)
    Depicts texturized, color portrait of Fulton and background image of “Clermont” on Hudson with onlooking colonists. Par Excellence Series Hudson River No. 1.
  - Koehler Hudson-Fulton Celebration Postcard, Large crease across top and several smaller creases in front upper left corner. Paper damaged in top right corner where image has worn away. (Box 1)
    Depicts color image of Hudson, Fulton, “Half-Moon,” and “Clermont”. Card includes the planned program for Hudson-Fulton Celebration.
  - Lounsbury Hudson Postcard, Image slightly faded along front top of card. (Box 1)
    Color sketch depicting Hendrik Hudson. Postcard for Hudson River Celebration. Copyright Fred C. Lounsbury.
  - Lounsbury Half-Moon Postcard, Small Stain on front upper right corner and right center. (Box 1)
    Color sketch depicting the “Half-Moon” on the Hudson River. Postcard for Hudson River Celebration. Copyright Fred C. Lounsbury.
  - Miller Fulton’s Clermont Postcard, Several creases along edges. Slight fraying/damage to corners and edges—more pronounced along bottom of card. (Box 1)
    Depicts color portrait of Fulton and image of “Clermont” on Hudson River.
  - Miller Hudson’s Half-Moon Postcard, Slight fraying on corners and crease in right bottom corner. (Box 1)
    Depicts color portrait of Hudson and image of “Half-Moon” on Hudson River.
  - Miller March of Progress Postcard, Large crease from top center to bottom right corner. (Box 1)
    Depicts color image of Fulton, Hudson, “Clermont,” “Half-Moon,” and Robert Fulton Steamship.
  - Newcomb Clermont Postcard, Small stains on front bottom right corner. Larger stain on front left center. (Box 1)
    Depicts color, mainly blue and yellow, image of “Clermont” on Hudson. Art by Frank Bittner.
  - Newcomb Start of Parade Postcard, Faint staining in front, top right corner and middle to bottom, center of image. (Box 1)
    Depicts color, mainly blue and yellow, image of the start of the Hudson-Fulton Celebration in NYC. Art by Frank Bittner.
  - Newcomb Half-Moon Postcard, Faint staining along front top, left, and bottom edges. (Box 1)
    Depicts color, mainly blue and yellow, image of Hudson’s “Half-Moon” on the Hudson River. Art by Frank Bittner.
  - Redfield Hudson Fulton Celebration Commission Postcard No. 1 (Box 1)
    Depicts color portrait of Henry Hudson with background image of Hudson’s “Half-Moon” on Hudson River.
  - Redfield Hudson Fulton Celebration Commission Postcard No. 2 (Box 1)
    Depicts color portrait of Fulton with background image of “Clermont” on Hudson River.
  - Redfield Hudson Fulton Celebration Commission Postcard No. 3 (Box 1)
    Depicts color drawing of History of New York title car float.
  - Redfield Hudson Fulton Celebration Commission Postcard No. 4 (Box 1)
    Depicts color drawing of Indian Period title car float.
  - Redfield Hudson Fulton Celebration Commission Postcard No. 5, Discoloration of corners from previous storage. (Box 1)
    Depicts color drawing of Legend of Hiawatha float.
  - Redfield Hudson Fulton Celebration Commission Postcard No. 6, Discoloration in all corners from previous storage. (Box 1)
    Depicts color drawing of Five Nations float.
  - Redfield Hudson Fulton Celebration Commission Postcard No. 7, Discoloration on front lower corner and all back corners from previous storage. (Box 1)
    Depicts color drawing of The First Sachem of the Iroquois float.
  - Redfield Hudson Fulton Celebration Commission Postcard No. 8 (Box 1)
    Depicts color drawing of Season of Blossoms float.
  - Redfield Hudson Fulton Celebration Commission Postcard No. 9, Very small stains on front upper and lower corners. (Box 1)
    Depicts color drawing of Season of Fruit float.
  - Redfield Hudson Fulton Celebration Commission Postcard No. 10, Discoloration of corners from previous storage. (Box 1)
    Depicts color drawing of the Season of Hunting float.
  - Redfield Hudson Fulton Celebration Commission Postcard No. 11, Slight discoloration in all corners from previous storage. (Box 1)
    Depicts color drawing of Season of Snows float.
  - Redfield Hudson Fulton Celebration Commission Postcard No. 12, Slight discoloration in all corners from previous storage. (Box 1)
    Depicts color drawing of War Dance float.
  - Redfield Hudson Fulton Celebration Commission Postcard No. 13, Slight discoloration in all corners from previous storage. (Box 1)
    Depicts color drawing of Dutch Period title car float.
  - Redfield Hudson Fulton Celebration Commission Postcard No. 14 (Box 1)
    Depicts color drawing of “Half-Moon” float.
  - Redfield Hudson Fulton Celebration Commission Postcard No. 15 (Box 1)
    Depicts color drawing of Fate of Henry Hudson float.
  - Redfield Hudson Fulton Celebration Commission Postcard No. 16, Slight discoloration in all corners from previous storage. (Box 1)
    Depicts color drawing of First Vessel Built on Manhattan float.
  - Redfield Hudson Fulton Celebration Commission Postcard No. 17, Slight damage of corners from indentations caused by previous storage. (Box 1)
    Depicts color drawing of Purchase of Manhattan float.
  - Redfield Hudson Fulton Celebration Commission Postcard No. 18, Slight damage of corners from indentations caused by previous storage. (Box 1)
    Depicts color drawing of Bronck’s Treaty with the Indians float.
  - Redfield Hudson Fulton Celebration Commission Postcard No. 19, Slight discoloration of corners from previous storage. (Box 1)
    Depicts color drawing of Reception of Peter Stuyvesant float.
  - Redfield Hudson Fulton Celebration Commission Postcard No. 20, Discoloration on back corners from previous storage. Staining across back middle. (Box 1)
    Depicts color drawing of Bowling on Bowling Green float.
  - Redfield Hudson Fulton Celebration Commission Postcard No. 21 (Box 1)
    Depicts color drawing of Gov. Leisler and the Huguenots float.
  - Redfield Hudson Fulton Celebration Commission Postcard No. 22, Slight crease on back middle bottom. Slight discoloration in all corners from past storage. (Box 1)
    Depicts color drawing of Dutch Doorway float.
  - Redfield Hudson Fulton Celebration Commission Postcard No. 23, Faint staining along back bottom. (Box 1)
    Depicts color drawing of Nieuw Amsterdam Becomes New York float.
  - Redfield Hudson Fulton Celebration Commission Postcard No. 24, Staining from front image across back. (Box 1)
    Depicts color drawing of Colonial Period title car float.
  - Redfield Hudson Fulton Celebration Commission Postcard No. 25, Discoloration imprinted lines on all corners from past storage. (Box 1)
    Depicts color drawing of Col. Schuyler and Indians at the St. James float.